A S M Shahadat Hossain

1315 W Lincoln Hwy, Apt. 200, DeKalb, IL 60115, USA asmhossain20@gmail.com (779) 902-0043 www.linkedin.com/in/asmshahadat

SUMMARY

A Data Science enthusiast with 3+ years of industry experience in Data Science, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Data Warehouse, Business Intelligence, Customer Insights Platforms, Operational Support Systems, and **DevOps Engineering** at renowned telecommunication companies having **49** to **83 million customers**.

EDUCATION

M.S. (ongoing) in Computer Science, Northern Illinois University, DeKalb, IL, USA

Expected May 2024

B.Sc. in Computer Science & Engineering, Rajshahi University of Engineering & Technology, Bangladesh

Feb 2018

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Computational Reproducibility, Data Science, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Software Engineering

PUBLICATION [Google Scholar]

Hossain, ASM Shahadat. "Customer segmentation using centroid based and density based clustering algorithms." In 2017 3rd International Conference on Electrical Information and Communication Technology (EICT), pp. 1-6. IEEE, 2017.

[Paper in IEEE XPlore]

[<u>PDF</u>]

(Number of Citations: 38)

RESEARCH PROJECTS

- Reproducibility of Visualizations in Jupyter Notebooks: Algorithms vs. Programmers Python Changes in visualizations upon rerunning Jupyter Notebooks were tracked and categorized. A set of survey questions was proposed to understand the differences between programmers' perceptions and algorithms for images.
- **Reproducibility of Jupyter Notebooks** [Details] Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Python Features were extracted from Jupyter Notebooks and 4 machine learning models such as Logistic Regression (LR), Extreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost), Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT), and Random Forest (RF) were built to automatically assess reproducibility with an accuracy of 62.2%.
- 'Reproducibility' in CS conferences [Details] Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Python Texts from 55 Computer Science conference websites mentioning reproducibility and 250 research papers from 55 such conferences as well as 25 conferences not mentioning reproducibility were used to understand how computer science conferences assess reproducibility of the submitted works and if there are any shared characteristics among the papers accepted in reproducibility-aware conferences.
- **Clinical Trials Categorization** [Details] Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Python 15 classification models including general purpose classifiers such as Decision Tree (DT), Support Vector Machine (SVM), Logistic Regression (LR), Naive Bayes (NB) as well as ensemble methods such as Random Forest (RF), Bagging, Adaboost, and XGBoost were used to classify clinical trials based on their Altmetric Attention Scores (AAS).
- **Comparative Study of Clustering Algorithms** [Details] [Related Publication] Machine Learning, Python A Comparative study of 2 clustering algorithms (K-means and DBSCAN) based on their performances on 3 datasets (IRIS Dataset, Wholesale Customer Dataset, and WEKA Unbalanced Dataset).

WORK EXPERIENCE

Graduate Teaching Assistant, Northern Illinois University, DeKalb, IL, USA

Aug 2020 - Present

Holding office hours, grading weekly assignments, quizzes, final exams, and proctoring exams for courses:

CSCI 240: Computer Programming in C++;

Fall 20, Spring 21

CSCI 330: UNIX and Network Programming;

Fall 21, Fall 22, Spring 23, Fall 23, Spring 24

CSCI 463: Computer Architecture and Systems Organization;

Spring 22

- Graduate Staff Assistant (Data Science & BI), Northern Illinois University, DeKalb, IL, USA

 Jun 2022 Sep 2022
 - Performed Data Migration from flat files to Snowflake (Cloud Computing-based Data Warehouse)
 - Detected and Corrected errors in 13 Python scripts caused due to System Migration (Windows to Linux)
 - Generated Data Visualization using Microsoft Power BI for Graduate Career and Professional Development
 - Ran processes on a Hybrid CPU/GPU Computing Cluster having 60 nodes capable of 30 teraFLOPS
 - Generated occupations and skills-based suggestions for graduate students by applying Data Science on Labor
 Market Data supplied by Emsi Burning Glass and 18K course syllabus documents
- Specialist (Operational Support Systems), Robi Axiata Limited, Dhaka, Bangladesh

May 2019 - Feb 2021

- Developed at least 10 scripts using Python, PL/SQL, Linux Shell, Windows PowerShell, and PHP to automate manual jobs and saved at least 4 man-hours per day which is approximately \$8K per year
- Performed System Administration of Network Management Systems developed by Huawei, Ericsson, and Nokia
- Provided Server Administration (Linux: Red Hat Linux, SUSE Linux, and Windows: 2012 R2, 2016) assistance
- Extended support to the automation Project Managers who used Agile and Scrum methods
- Analyzed network performance data of approximately 50 million subscribers by using tools and scripts
- Jr. Engineer (Business Intelligence Data Warehouse), Grameenphone IT Ltd, Dhaka, Bangladesh Jul 2018 May 2019
 - Performed Developments and Operations of ETL (Extract, Transform, Load) using SQL in Oracle servers
 - Investigated Data trend Mismatch from revenue up to \$40K per day
 - Generated monthly High-Value customer database from 83 million subscribers using PL/SQL
- Project Engineer, Transmission Modernization, Robi Axiata Limited, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Apr 2018 - Jun 2018

- Supported in Project Management (Agile) and Vendor Management
- Initiated and monitored at least 10 Network Change Requests per day for 3G to 4G network upgradation

SKILLS

- Data Analysis: Machine Learning, and Natural Language Processing using Python libraries such as NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, NLTK, Gensim, Matplotlib, Seaborn, OpenCV, SpaCy, SciPy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, and Keras
- **Data Management**: Enterprise Data Warehousing, Business Intelligence Data Integration, ETL (Extract, Transform, Load) in Oracle, MySQL, and Microsoft SQL Server
- Data Visualization: Tableau, Microsoft Excel, Microsoft Power BI, and JavaScript D3
- Automation: tasks automation using Python, PL/SQL, JAVA, Bash, Windows PowerShell, and PHP
- System and Server Administration: Red Hat Linux, SUSE Linux, and Windows: 2012 R2, 2016
- Interpersonal Skills: leadership, teamwork, conflict management, patience, and communication

CERTIFICATIONS, AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

IBM AI Engineering Professional Certificate

[Credentials]

Machine Learning - Certificate of completion of an 11-week course with Stanford Online

[Credentials]

- Top 25 Employees: Among more than 1400 employees at Robi Axiata Ltd, Bangladesh for AI Upskilling Program
- Top 100 Learners: Among more than 1400 employees at Robi Axiata Ltd, Bangladesh for times in online learning
- Divisional Champion, National Collegiate Programming Contest (NCPC) 2015, Bangladesh
- Honorable Mentions in ACM ICPC Dhaka regional online preliminary 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016

SERVICES

Volunteer (Evaluation), STEM Fest sponsored by Meta and hosted by Northern Illinois University

2021, 2022, 2023

Problem Setter & Judge, Programming contests at RUET Analytical Programming Lab

Jan 2015 - Jan 2016

• Student **Program Committee**, 13th International Conference on the Theory of Information Retrieval **SIGIR (ICTIR)**

2023

Reviewer at The 3rd International Conference on Electrical, Computer, Communications and Mechatronics Engineering
(ICECCME), The 3rd International Conference on Electrical, Computer and Energy Technologies (ICECET), International
Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Control, Data Sciences and Applications (ACDSA)